<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Notes]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/</link><image><url>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Notes</title><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/</link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 15:16:29 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 15:16:29 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></copyright><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator>Yujie He</dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Ideal gas]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Ideal gas: gases in which intermolecular forces and the volume occupied by the molecules are treated as totally negligible. In this case the pressure arises solely from the kinetic motions of the molecules<br>Different forms of the ideal gas equation: <br>
<br>In terms of the ideal gas constant  and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amount_of_substance" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amount_of_substance" target="_blank">amount of substance</a> <br>

<br>In terms of the Stefan-Boltzmann constant  and the number of particles 

where , and  is the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avogadro_constant" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Avogadro_constant" target="_blank">Avogadro constant</a>
<br>In terms of density (divide both sides by total mass of the system) 

where  is the mean molecular weight (mean mass per gas molecule in units of proton mass)
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/ideal-gas.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Ideal gas.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 14:13:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Blackbody Radiation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Thermodynamical equilibrium = detailed balance = blackbody radiation = 
<br><br>The <a class="internal-link" data-href="Radiative Transfer.md" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Intensity</a> (or brightness) of thermal radiation, energy emitted per unit time per unit area per frequency/wavelength per solid angle, unit ergs/s/cm2/sr/Hz. Systems that is thermalized (detailed balance) emits blackbody radiation.<br><br><br>In the form of <a class="internal-link" data-href="Radiative Transfer.md" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">energy density</a>, integrate out solid angle  and divided by , ,<br><br><br><br>Intergration of intensity over all frequencies yields the energy emitted per unit time per unit area.<br><br><br>Energy density .<br>where  is the Boltzmann constant. Also  is what we call the radiation flux (erg/s/cm2) c.f. <a data-href="Radiative Transfer#Concepts and Terminology of Radiation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html#Concepts_and_Terminology_of_Radiation" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Radiative Transfer &gt; Concepts and Terminology of Radiation</a><br>Hence the luminosity of a spherical black body of radius  is readily<br><br><br>Recall from <a data-href="Laws of Thermodynamics" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Laws of Thermodynamics</a>,<br><br>Einstein 引入这样的跃迁概率系数，用来解释Planck公式为什么是这样的形式。<br>（受激）吸收概率系数：在辐射强度为  的辐射场的作用下，单位时间内一个原子在  立体角内吸收能量为  的光子从较低的  能级跃迁到较高的  能级的概率为 ；<br>
自发发射概率系数：在没有外场的情况下，单位时间一个原子从高能级  跃迁到低能级  同时在  立体角内发射一个能量为  光子的概率为 <br>
受激发射概率系数：在辐射强度为  的辐射场的作用下，单位时间一个原子从高能级  跃迁到低能级  同时在  立体角内发射一个能量为  光子的概率为  （另一种定义是在辐射密度为的辐射场下）<br>在热动平衡下存在着细致平衡原理，<br><br>于是<br><br>在热动平衡下带入 Boltzmann 公式 (<a data-href="Boltzmann &amp; Saha Equation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/boltzmann-&amp;-saha-equation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Boltzmann &amp; Saha Equation</a>)，就能得到黑体辐射公式的基本形式。常数可以通过和原公式对比得到（而原公式和实验符合得很好，其实就是和实验对比得到待定系数）<br><br>对比和实验符合得很好的 Planck 公式就可以得到三个爱因斯坦系数之间满足的关系，对任意两个能级，知其一则知其三。<br><br>For alternative definition of  by radiation energy density, the pre-factor in the first equation is .<br>These relations can equivalently be derived by considering thermodynamic equilibrium (detailed balance) in blackbody radiation field<br><br><br>Rybicki, Radiative Processes in Astrophysics<br>For thermal radiation , which means<br><br>Thermal radiation: ; blackbody radiation (which is a form of thermal radiation): . Thermal radiation becomes blackbody radiation only for optically thick media.<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/blackbody-radiation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Blackbody Radiation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 08:58:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Eddington Luminosity, Eddington Limit]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The theoretical maximum luminosity that can be emitted when radiation pressure and gravity are in equilibrium in a spherical geometry.<br>
See <a data-href="Stellar Model" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/stellar-model.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stellar Model</a><br><br>Then<br><br>If this luminosity is powered by accretion, then it gives the Eddington accretion limit by equating the ress mass energy released in unit time to the Eddington luminosity<br><br>Then it follows<br><br>Where . Note than an "equally common definition" is .<br>Another definition that I found in the internet is<br><br>Then<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/eddington-limit.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Eddington Limit.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 13:33:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hydrodynamics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
Provided we are interested only in lengthscales  (the mean free path) we can regard the gas as a continuous fluid, having velocity , temperature  and density  defined as each point. ... Note that these equations of gas dynamics may not always be applicable. For example, these equations may themselves predict large changes in gas properties over lengthscales comparable with ; under these circumstances the fluid approximations is invalid and we must use the deeper but more complicated approach of the plasma kinetic theory.
<br><br>Continuity equations<br><br>Euler equations (conservation of momentum)<br><br>
<br>: force per unit volume. For example, gravity: <br>
Equivalently


<br> for ideal fluid.
<br>Complete equation: <br>
Energy conservation

Or more explicitly, for example for an ideal fluid


<br>where  is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Laws of Thermodynamics" data-href="Laws of Thermodynamics" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">enthalpy per unit mass</a>. 
<br><br>The energy equation for an ideal fluid above can equivalently be written as<br><br>For constant gravity potential we then have<br><br>where  is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Laws of Thermodynamics" data-href="Laws of Thermodynamics" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">entropy per unit mass</a>.<br>In fact with full self-gravity, we have  regardless of whether the potential is statis or not.<br><br>and  (<a data-href="Newtonian gravity" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/newtonian-gravity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Newtonian gravity</a>). <br><br><br>For an ideal fluid and steady flow (),<br><br>This can be shown from energy conservation equation.<br><br><br>where  is the 3D metric (which  in Cartisian coord).  is the bulk viscosity.  is the shear viscosity.<br><br>where .<br>The famous Navier-Stokes equation is the momentum conservation equation/Euler equation for isotropic fluids with viscosity<br><br>It is the generalisation of  and .<br><br>
<br>Modern Classical Physics, Thorne and Blandford
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/hydrodynamics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Hydrodynamics.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 09:41:08 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hydrostatics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>From static equilibrium of a small volume, the difference of the pressure on the inside and outside of the volume is gravity on the small volume.<br><br>Or in the view of equilibrium, pressure from inside (pointing outward) = pressure from outside (pointing inward) + gravity (pointing inward). <br><br>Therefore we have the differential equation in Euler description,<br><br>Or in Lagrangian description, multiplying [the mass distribution function](Stellar%20Model.md Model&gt;) on both sides, <br><br><br><br>For non-equilibrium cases,<br><br>Therefore,<br><br>
<br>Gravity dominates<br>
is of the same magnitude with [free fall scale](Star%20Formation.md Formation&gt;)
<br>Pressure gradient dominates

where  is the [sound speed](Thermodynamic%20Process.md Process&gt;)
<br><br><br>with ideal gas<br><br>where<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/hydrostatics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Hydrostatics.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 14:20:38 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Interstellar Medium]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Thermodynamic Equilibrium: detailed balance (every process is balanced exactly by its counterprocess) - untrue both globally and locally (no LTE), in constrast to, e.g., stellar interiors.<br>
<br>Maxwell distribution of particle kinetic energies: generally valid 
<br>Planck distribution of radiation energies: not generally valid
<br>Boltzmann distribution of level population: not generally valid
<br>Define excitation temperature  (per level)<br>
Statistical equilibrium, weaker condition than thermal equilibrium, is valid]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/interstellar-medium.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Interstellar Medium.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Dec 2024 14:55:31 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Interstellar Turbulence]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Johns Hopkins Turbulence Database (JHTDB): <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://turbulence.pha.jhu.edu/" target="_blank">http://turbulence.pha.jhu.edu/</a><br>A g kritsuk, 2017, the structure and statistics of interstellar turbulence
Turbulence is ubiquitous in the interstellar medium (ISM) [1]. It organizes the ISM structure to optimize and direct energy fluxes across an enormous range of length scales within the Milky Way disk. Interstellar turbulence, however, differs from the familiar Kolmogorov homogeneous and isotropic incompressible case [2, 3] in several important respects: it is neither isotropic nor homogeneous [4]; the interstellar gas is highly compressible and magnetized; and its thermal energy is not strictly conserved. Instead, the ISM-specific radiative cooling and volumetric heating functions determine an equilibrium multiphase nature of the neutral ISM [5, 6, 7]. Nonlinear advection couples with nonlinear radiative cooling, further complicating the treatment of the ISM. We hence deal with a classical example of a hierarchical nonequilibrium dissipative system, receiving energy primarily at large scales (∼ 100 pc) from stellar feedback, extragalactic gas accretion, large-scale shear, and gravitational instabilities within the disk and loosing energy through small-scale dissipation (10−4 pc) and local radiative cooling [8].
<br><br>Kolmogorov's theory in homogeneous and isotropic incompressible turbulence. Interstellar turbulence, however, differs with this scenario in several important respects: it is neither isotropic nor homogeneous; the interstellar gas is highly compressible and magnetized; and its thermal energy is not strictly conserved.<br>Big whorls have little whorls,<br>
which feed on their velocity;<br>
And little whorls have lesser whorls,<br>
And so on to viscosity<br>from: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/13161/physical-explanation-for-kolmogorov-5-3-spectrum-in-fluid-mechanics" target="_blank">https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/13161/physical-explanation-for-kolmogorov-5-3-spectrum-in-fluid-mechanics</a><br>The standard explanation is that there is a constant flux of energy from large eddies to smaller eddies. The time scale  for an eddy of scale  to turn over is the energy density for scale  is , so you get an energy flux rate  which is assumed constant. You then estimate the spectral energy density as <br><img alt="Kolmogorov-scaling-in-the-inertial-range.jpg" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/kolmogorov-scaling-in-the-inertial-range.jpg">]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/interstellar-turbulence.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Interstellar Turbulence.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 13:34:25 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/kolmogorov-scaling-in-the-inertial-range.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/kolmogorov-scaling-in-the-inertial-range.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Multiwavelengths Astronomy]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="Pasted image 20220721000248.png" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20220721000248.png"><br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/multiwavelengths-astronomy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Multiwavelengths Astronomy.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 13:08:57 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20220721000248.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20220721000248.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Newtonian Gravity]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Gravitational Wave" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/gravitational-wave.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gravitational Wave</a><br>What we know is that objects tends to move towards each other. A larger "amount" of matter bears a larger tendency in this sense. And a theory of gravitation allows us to calculate how they move under this tendency.<br><br>Newton's theory of gravity. In the language of force<br><br>and then<br>
In the language of gravitational potential <br>
and the acceleration is given by the gradient (descent) of the potential<br>
therefore gravitational acceleration has<br><br><br>In applications of Hydrodynamics, it is useful to express the gravitation in terms of <a data-href="Stress tensor" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/stress-tensor.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stress tensor</a>,<br><br><br>Gravitational potential is define as the work produced by gravitation to move the mass points away from each other to infinitely far away, where the zero point is set, i.e. . <br><br><br>For a sphere of radius  and total mass  with constant density, the self gravitational potential energy is<br><br>Proof<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/newtonian-gravity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Newtonian gravity.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 13:49:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pressure Integral]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br><br>具有动量  的单个粒子对容器壁的压力的贡献为,<br><br>其中  是粒子和容器壁的作用时间的一半,  是粒子和容器壁碰撞作用的半程距离（只是作用的距离，与容器的大小无关）<br><br>其中  为系统中动量大小处于区间  的粒子数， 为单位体积中动量大小处于区间  的粒子数。<br>这式子称作压强积分<br><br><br><br>Using Maxwell-Boltzmann Distribution<br>
Finally<br>
<br><br>Where  is the <a class="internal-link" data-href="Radiative Transfer.md" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">energy density of radiation</a>, using Planck formula (<a data-href="Blackbody Radiation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/blackbody-radiation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Blackbody Radiation</a>),<br><br>And  here corresponds to the radiation pressure mentioned in <a class="internal-link" data-href="Radiative Transfer.md" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">radiation</a> in the following way<br><br>Where<br>
Therefore<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/pressure-integral.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Pressure Integral.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 12:03:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Radiative Transfer]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
When the scale of a system greatly exceeds the wavelength of radiation, we can consider radiation to travel in straight lines in free space or homogeneous media -- from this fact a substantial theory (transfer theory) can be erected.
<br><br>Radiation intensity, or brightness , energy emitted per unit time per unit area per frequency/wavelength per solid angle. Let dEν be the energy in radiation at frequency ν, in frequency interval dν, from solid angle dΩ, flowing through an area dA, in a time interval dt :<br><br><br>
<br>units: erg s-1 cm-2 sr-1 Hz-1. 
<br>sr: steradian,  for full sky
<br>An alternative, equivalent way to express specific intensity is by the photon occupation number <br><br>
<br>(Rayleigh-Jeans) brightness temperature, equals to thermal temperature in radio regime <br>

<br>Flux: <br>
<br>Net flux 


<br>Proof of inverse square law, for a uniformly bright sphere of radius :


where . At , we have , the flux at the surface of a uniformly bright sphere is  times its brightness/intensity. 
<br>Luminosity  (erg/s), total radiative energy that leaves one object<br><br>over surface area. Could also be monochromatic , the unit is then (erg/s/Hz).<br>Momentum flux  (recall momentum of a photon )<br><br>Average intensity <br><br>Energy density  (erg cm-3 Hz-1) divide over  to change to per volume, instead of per area<br><br>Radiative pressure (for a reflecting surface)  (momentum per unit time per unit area = pressure)<br><br>
<br>Each photon transfer twice its normal component of momentum on reflection
<br>For an isotropic radiation field, this integrates (over  steradian instead of ) to .
<br>Radiation force<br>
First: radiation flux vector<br><br>Then radiation force (per unit volume) is:<br><br><br><br>The surface brightness of a galaxy  is the amount of light on the sky at a particular point  on the image. Consider a small patch of side  in a galaxy located at a angular diameter distance  and luminosity distance . It will subtend an angle  on the sky. If the combined luminosity of all the stars in this region is , its apparent brightness is .<br>
Therefore the surface brightness<br>
Note the last equation holds only under a flat geometry! (See <a data-href="Cosmological Distances" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/cosmological-distances.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cosmological Distances</a>) The appropriate units of  are .<br><br>
<br>Optical depth , the dimensionless -folding factor for absorption

: optically thick; : optically thin
<br>Emission coefficient 


<br>Absorption coefficient  ()

The radiative transfer equation is:

Or equivalently in the form:

where the source function is defined as . 
<br><br>The radiative transfer equation (with the source function) have a formal solution which can be found by multiplying  on both sides and integrating by parts, it is<br><br>for constant ,<br><br> is the intensity that  tends to approach (as  increases), and do not approach if  not sufficiently large.<br><br>
<br>《恒星大气物理》汪珍如 曲钦岳
<br>Rijksuniversiteit Groningen galaxy course: <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.astro.rug.nl/~ahelmi/galaxies_course/class_VII-E/ellip-06.pdf" target="_blank">https://www.astro.rug.nl/~ahelmi/galaxies_course/class_VII-E/ellip-06.pdf</a>
<br>Lecture notes of Paul van der Werf, Interstellar Medium
<br>Radiative Processes in Astrophysics, George B. Rybicki, Alan P. Lightman
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/radiative-transfer.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Radiative Transfer.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 10:40:05 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Star Formation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Warning
Some of these notes I took during my bachelors in Nanjing University and are in Chinese.
<br><br>根据[位力定理](Virial%20Theorem.md Theorem&gt;)，自引力束缚的平衡系统有<br><br>其中 , . 考虑一个自引力束缚的分子云，若  则动能主导，分子云膨胀。若 则引力势能主导，分子云坍缩。由此可以导出分子云坍缩的金斯判据。<br>对一个忽略旋转，湍动，磁场，密度均匀()的球对称单原子分子云，其[自引力势能](Gravitation%20Law.md Law&gt;)为<br><br>根据[能量均分定理](Equipartition%20Theorem.md Theorem&gt;)，分子云的热运动动能为<br><br>由判据即可得金斯判据<br><br>其中分别称金斯质量，金斯半径。上二式称恒星形成的金斯判据。<br><br>Taken from Joop's Large Scale Structures and Galaxy Formation<br><br>Substituting the expression for sound speed (<a data-href="Thermodynamic Process#Application derivation of sound speed" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/thermodynamic-process.html#Application_derivation_of_sound_speed" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Thermodynamic Process &gt; Application derivation of sound speed</a>)<br><br>For monatomic gas<br><br><br>解运动方程得到的分子云坍缩自由下落时标为<br><br>
<br>同调坍缩 Homogeneous collapse
<br>由内而外坍缩 Inside-out collapse (初始密度不均匀，内部较致密的巨分子云)
<br><br>下面由第一性原理出发推导上式，考虑一个初始半径 ，初始密度均匀为  的分子云。初期气体自身压强忽略，光学薄，引力势能释放不受阻，等温坍缩。处于距离分子云中心  处的质量元的牛顿运动方程为<br><br>其中<br>
<br>Solution<br>
<br>
Multiply  on both sides and integrate twice.<br>
Integrate over , i.e., <br>
Integrate again . Note that during the collapse  retracts while  stays the same. The matter inside a spherical shell of radius  moves inward along with  and stays inside the shell.<br>


<br>
When <br>


<br>
Let , <br>


<br>
Let  and integrate<br>
Integration yields<br>


<br>
When <br>


<br>As  goes from  to ,  goes from  to . Take , the  obtained is .]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/star-formation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Star Formation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 12:51:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stellar Model]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>
<br>
Mass distribution<br>


<br>
Hydrodynamics equilibrium<br>


<br>
Energy equation<br>
Where<br>
<br>


<br>
Energy transfer equation

<br>Radiation<br>
convection if <br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/stellar-model.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Stellar Model.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 10:37:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stress tensor]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The stress tensor (we denote as ) reports the force exerted when a surface is inserted:<br><br>where the indices run through . Or more explicitly,  is the  component of force per unit area (pressure) across a surface perpendicular to ; it is also (by ), the  component of momentum that crosses a unit area that is perpendicular to , per unit time, with the crossing being from  to .<br>We also have the pressure<br><br> being the normal unit vector of the surface.<br>The (any real world) stress tensor is always symmetric, because otherwise the material would exert a torque that set itself spinning and forever faster. To balance the torque, the stress tensor must be symmetric:<br><br>Reference:<br>
<br>Blandford and Thorne, Modern classical physics
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/stress-tensor.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Stress tensor.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 15:29:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Virial theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The Virial theorem is of vital importance in astronomy and astrophysics.<br>For a stable system of discrete particles, bound by a conservative force (forces characterized exclusively by their work), with that of the total potential energy of the system. Mathematically, the theorem states<br><br>If the force between any two particles of the system results from a potential energy  that is proportional to some power n of the interparticle distance , the virial theorem takes the simple form<br><br>For gravity , the virial theorem for gravitational bounded system is<br>
This is often written as<br><br>For a gravitationally bound test particle<br><br><br>For a system of mass&nbsp;&nbsp;and radius&nbsp;&nbsp;with constant density, the gravitational energy per unit mass is&nbsp;. The kinetic energy per unit mass is&nbsp;<br><br><br>The formation of a dynamic equilibrium in a system of collisionless particles modelled as being subject only to Newtonian gravity (galaxy, other stellar system, or galaxy cluster).]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/virial-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Astrophysics/Virial Theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 10:32:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Black Hole]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Black Hole Ringdown" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/black-hole-ringdown.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Black Hole Ringdown</a><br>
<a data-href="Gravitational Wave" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/gravitational-wave.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gravitational Wave</a><br>
For observation, see <a data-href="Measuring BHs" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/Measuring BHs" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Measuring BHs</a><br>Classification<br><br><br>While the mass of a black hole can take any positive value, the charge and angular momentum are constrained by the mass. The total electric charge&nbsp;Q and the total angular momentum&nbsp;J are expected to satisfy the inequality<br>
<br>the dimensionless spin parameter can be defined as <br>
there is also  called Kerr parameter or angular parameter per unit mass, which, in geometrical units, is in .<br><br>
<br>Surface gravity  is a constant everywhere on event horizon.
<br>Compare 2 black hole that differ only in , ,

 is the surface angular momentum,  is the surface area . An analogy with ...?
<br>.
<br>Impossible to reduce  in a finite number of steps.

Reference<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_hole" target="_blank">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_hole</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/338836/explain-kerr-newmann-black-hole-spins-in-si-units" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/338836/explain-kerr-newmann-black-hole-spins-in-si-units" target="_blank">Explain Kerr-Newmann Black Hole Spins in SI Units</a>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/black-hole.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Black Hole and Gravitational Wave/Black Hole.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 18:00:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Black Hole Ringdown]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Gravitational Wave" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/gravitational-wave.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gravitational Wave</a><br>
<a data-href="Black Hole" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/black-hole.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Black Hole</a><br><br>
<br>Inspiral<br>
analytically described by the post-Newtonian approximation
<br>Merger<br>
Weak field approximation invalid. Numerical Relativity simulation required.
<br>Ringdown (See <a data-href="Black Hole Ringdown" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/black-hole-ringdown.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Black Hole Ringdown</a>)<br>
Black hole quasinormal modes. "A black hole is completely described by its quasinormal modes, and the detection of a single quasinormal mode is sufficient to completely determine the spacetime of astrophysical black holes."<br>
Fundamental quadrupolar mode - detected in 22 events.<br>
Secondary quasinormal mode<br>
In analogy to the standard electromagnetic spectroscopy, the multimode analysis of the quasinormal modes is known as black hole spectroscopy.
<br>The end state of astrophysical binary black hole (BBH) mergers is a perturbed single BH characterized by two parameters: the final remnant mass  and spin angular momentum .<br>A perturbed BH emit GW in three stages:<br>
<br>The transient is the first stage and depends on the initial perturbation
<br>The quasinormal modes stage is the first stage and they are damped sinusoidal solutions. The amplitudes and phases of these modes are determined by the transient
<br>In the last stage the oscillattion ceases with a power-law tail
<br>(Gravitational waves, Michele Maggiore)<br>
The numerical simulations shows that, for an equal-mass non-spinning BH binary, the final BH mass and spin are<br><br>about  of the total mass of the BBH is radiated away in GW. <br><br>The QNM frequencies are fully characterized by the remnant BH parameters, but their amplitudes and phases depend on the initial perturbation.<br>
For a distant observer, the ringdown waveform written as the sum of the polarizations  and  basis of the quasinormal modes is given by<br>
Where  is spin-weighted spherical harmonics. The modes with  are called fundamental modes,  called the overtones.<br>Harmonic mode <br>
<br>
<br>Most prominant  harmonic , dominant mode 
<br>Other strongest modes include <br>
For example, a nonspinning circular binary with mass ratio q = 1 does not excite the harmonics with odd m. - But gwsurrogate does generate non-zero waveform for mode_list = [(3,3)]?
<br>higher overtones  decay faster
<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevX.9.041060" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevX.9.041060" target="_blank">Black Hole Ringdown: The Importance of Overtones</a> :<br>
The QNM frequencies are denoted , where  and  describe the angular dependence of a mode and , the often-ignored integer overtone index, sorts QNMs with the same angular dependence by how quickly they decay. The slowest decaying fundamental mode, , is often considered to be of primary importance, while the more quickly decaying overtones are often disregarded. However, we find that the overtones are not necessarily subdominant as is often assumed, but instead, they can dominate the early part of the ringdown.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/black-hole-ringdown.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Black Hole and Gravitational Wave/Black Hole Ringdown.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 11:32:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gravitational Wave]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Newtonian gravity" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/newtonian-gravity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Newtonian gravity</a><br>
First indirect measurement: PSR 1913+16, orbit decays = loss of energy due to GW wave emission<br>
First direct detection: LIGO, GW150913<br>
<br><br>"non-inertial movements in the source produce radiation"<br>
<br>2 polarizations: plus () and cross ().<br>
<img alt="Pasted image 20230226193140.png" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20230226193140.png">
<br>Dominated by quadrupole moment <br>
No monopole moments  total mass-energy conservation<br>
No dipole moments  center of mass-energy and total angular momentum conservation
<br>Hard to detect, <br>

<br><br>4km LIGO, US: detection since 2015<br>
600m GEO600, German<br>
3km Virgo, Italian: detection since 2017<br>
3km KAGRA, Japan: begin 2020<br>
LIGO, Virgo, and KAGRA Collaboration = LVKC<br>
LISA ~2030s<br>
TianQin ~2030s<br><br><img alt="Pasted image 20230322163105.png" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20230322163105.png">]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/black-hole-and-gravitational-wave/gravitational-wave.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Black Hole and Gravitational Wave/Gravitational Wave.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 11:30:01 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20230226193140.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20230226193140.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Angle bracket notations in cosmology]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The meaning of angle brackets  often depends on the context. It generally means the expectation value or ensemble average over different realizations. It could mean one of the following<br>
<br>The average quantity  of different realization of the universe under same cosmology
<br>When ergodicity is assumed, 
<br>When  is promoted to a (set of) quantum operator, the expectation value follows with the  
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/angle-bracket-notations-in-cosmology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Angle bracket notations in cosmology.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 13:32:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Big Bang Nuclear synthesis (BBN)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>reference: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.mv.helsinki.fi/home/hkurkisu/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.mv.helsinki.fi/home/hkurkisu/" target="_blank">Hannu Kurki-Suonio</a>'s cosmology lecture notes. <br><br>Hannu's cosmology ii (2022), p84
According to the second law of thermodynamics the total entropy of the universe never decreases; it either stays constant or increases. An increase in entropy is always related to a deviation from thermodynamic equilibrium. It turns out that any entropy production in the various known processes in the universe is totally insignificant compared to the total entropy of the universe56, which is huge, and dominated by the relativistic species. Thus it is an excellent approximation to treat the expansion of the universe as adiabatic, so that the total entropy stays constant, i.e.<br>

]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/big-bang-nucleosynthesis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Big Bang Nucleosynthesis.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 14:21:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cluster Cosmology]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.star.bris.ac.uk/bjm/lectures/cluster-cosmology/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.star.bris.ac.uk/bjm/lectures/cluster-cosmology/" target="_blank">Nice lecture slides for cluster cosmology</a><br><br>X-ray Luminosity (from images or spectra) depends strongly on , more weakly on . Bremsstrahlung emission from hot ionized gas.<br>Emissivity of a bremsstrahlung-emitting plasma is<br><br> is energy emitted per unit frequency, time and volume.  are number densities of electrons and ions.  is charge on ion. Then<br><br>X-ray Temperature  (from spectra) - Fitting to observed X-ray spectra give temperature of the intra-cluster medium (ICM).  in range  to  keV. Gas are heated to these temperatures during cluster formation.  (kinetic energy) -virial theorem-&gt; cluster mass.<br>Metal abundances in ICM (from spectra)<br>Density of ICM (from surface brightness profile)<br>Overdensity Radii  - A radius within which the mean density is  times the critical density () at the cluster's redshift. Denoted as . And the total mass within  is denoted as .  and recall from <a data-href="Friedmann Equations" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/friedmann-equations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Friedmann Equations</a>, . <br>Simulations show  virial radius: radius separating relaxed part of cluster from infalling material.  is radius measured out to in typical X-ray observations. <br>If a galaxy cluster is dynamically relaxed (no recent mergers) we expect the gas and galaxies to be virialized (<a data-href="Virial Theorem" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/virial-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Virial Theorem</a>). <br><br>Self-similar model assumes: <br>
<br>Clusters form in single collapse at 
<br>Gravity only source of energy<br>
Self-similar model predicts:  
<br>Clusters of different masses are scaled versions 
<br>Clusters at different  identical if scaled for  (This is where  comes in)
<br><img alt="Pasted image 20240119102924.png" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20240119102924.png"><br>
From Kostas' DMDE lecture<br>Two key point of the scaling relation is the <a data-href="Virial Theorem" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/virial-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Virial Theorem</a> and X-ray emissivity and luminosity's dependence on total mass.<br>
where . Recall from <a data-href="Virial Theorem" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/virial-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Virial Theorem</a> we know that , therefore <br>X-ray emissivity &amp; luminosity<br>
Emissivity  and luminosity . Therefore<br><br>So <br>Also (derivation needed?)<br><br>From , ,  relations we can readily obtain , , ,<br><br><br><br>for soft x-ray we expect  instead of 2. Other  related relations also differs as listed. <br><br><br><br>For  and  relations<br><br>For <br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/cluster-cosmology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Cluster Cosmology.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 23:14:48 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20240119102924.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20240119102924.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cosmic Microwave Background]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://background.uchicago.edu/~whu/intermediate/intermediate.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://background.uchicago.edu/~whu/intermediate/intermediate.html" target="_blank">Great interactive website by Wayne Hu</a><br><img alt="Pasted image 20231202234215.png" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20231202234215.png">]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/cosmic-microwave-background.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Cosmic Microwave Background.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 02 Dec 2023 22:42:22 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20231202234215.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/lib/media/pasted-image-20231202234215.png"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cosmological Distances]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>as in FLRW metric (see <a data-href="Friedmann Equations#Friedmann-Robertson-Walker-Lemaître Metric" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/friedmann-equations.html#Friedmann-Robertson-Walker-Lemaître_Metric" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Friedmann Equations &gt; Friedmann-Robertson-Walker-Lemaître Metric</a>)<br><br><br>The integration can be translate to for radial distances<br><br>Watch out the square root sign. Choose the sign based on your problem, e.g. a light ray from  or to .<br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/cosmological-distances.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Cosmological Distances.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 23:14:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dark Matter]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Dark Matter vs Modified Gravity<br>
Stacy S. McGaugh et al. PRL 2016 -&gt; modified gravity?<br>Dark matter: lots of work, but null result<br>
Dark energy: not much work, getting active recently<br>
Far from solving the problem<br><br>cold dark matter: zero temperature -&gt; infinite hierarchical to small scale<br>
but observation observed a 'lower bound', where no halo lower than that mass is found -&gt; maybe there is none, maybe they are not with galaxies<br>
Gravitational wave cosmology might be able to solve this]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/dark-matter.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Dark Matter.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2023 11:22:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Energy Conservation in Cosmology]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A vector field  is a Killing vector if it preserves the metric under its flow:<br><br>In FLRW metric, the only nontrivial Christoffels are:<br><br>The Lie derivative is<br><br>Thus, the time vector  is not a Killing vector unless , i.e., unless the scale factor is constant (i.e., static spacetime). This is approximately true in the Minkowski limit, infinitely far back in time, .<br>If a particle moves in a spacetime with a timelike Killing vector , then the quantity:<br><br>is conserved along the geodesic (where ).<br>But if no such  exists (e.g., in FRW), then this "energy" is not conserved — e.g., photons redshift:<br><br>Even more generally, in GR, the local conservation law:<br><br>does not imply global conservation of energy unless spacetime symmetries (Killing vectors) exist.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/energy-conservation-in-cosmology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Energy Conservation in Cosmology.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 May 2025 14:26:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Friedmann Equations]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Dark Matter" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/dark-matter.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Dark Matter</a><br>
<a data-href="Hubble Parameter" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/hubble-parameter.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hubble Parameter</a><br><br>The universe is homogeneous and isotropic + Copernican principle "We are not in a special place".<br><br>Referece: Sean Carroll Spacetime and Geometry<br>
Use  convention and geometrical unit <br>
In  coordinates<br><br>alternatively in  comoving coordinates<br><br>(They are not only equivalent, but also equal.)<br>There are two conventions of dimensions here<br>
<br>Dimensionless scale factor , curvature  of dimension , and  of dimension . Often adopted in astronomy. In this choice  can take arbitrary values.
<br>Scale factor  of dimension , dimensionless curvature , and dimensionless comoving coordinates . In this choice . And  is sometimes denoted as .
<br>The spatial curvature is characterized by the Ricci scalar contracted from the spatial part of metric , which in FLRW metric is<br><br>In either conventiosn,  has the dimension of . To see what this result means, we note that the curvature of a sphere is . Thus for positive curvature, we say the geometry of the universe is sphere-like, and the radius of the sphere is , or  for the  convention. <br>We also see that  expansion drives . <br><br><br><br><br>Note: <br>
<br>Two out of the three equations are independent
<br>The third equation is sometimes called the continuity equation.
<br>For a homogeneous scalar field, the third equation gives the inflation field equation of motion .
<br>Solutions to the Friedmann equations<br><br><br>The Friedmann Equation can fomally be derived from Newtonian physics, without General Relativity. It is not a GR effect. Consider a ball with radius . The total mass inside the ball would be . Assume that there is no matter exchange between inside and the outside of the ball, hence the mass  stays constant.<br>Start from Newton's second law<br><br>imposing a useful transformation<br><br>The result can be easily integrated, denoting the integration constant as  on the LHS<br><br>Expressing . Here  changes as  to make  constant over time. Then we have<br><br>You might want to ask, in Friedmann equations we take into account for radiation (relativistic matter which scales with ) and dark energy (which is guessed to scale with some  we are not sure of), where are those stuff here? It's because they are not thought to interact with gravity in newtonian physics. <br>Also directly from Newton's second law, divide the equation by  gives the second Friedmann equation, but without the pressure term.<br><br>Why Einstein’s equations are needed if ? – For non-relativistic matter , while for the relativistic matter . Meaning the pressure term is only important to describe gravitation of relativistic matter.<br><br>The Friedmann equation can be written as<br><br>it follows<br><br>integration yields<br><br>Initial condition  when , so the integration constant is . And the result<br><br>From here we also have some other important implications. Such as the relativistic matter density in radiation dominated universe (early universe)<br><br>Combining the relativistic matter (matter with ) density as a function of temperature (this equation is deduced by integrating the BE and FD distribution)<br><br>we can deduce temperature as a function of time or the scale factor in the early radiation dominated epoch ( units)<br><br><br>We can rewrite the first Friedmann equation by<br><br>Matter combination decides everything: the curvature of the universe, the acceleration/deceleration of the universe.<br>
and the Friedmann equation can be written as This sum equals one hold true at any cosmic time because of the Friedman equation and some clever definition of , which is not actually the density of anything!<br>
Or in more useful form, multiply by <br><br>where<br><br>And  relates to  by <br><br>which means the curvature of the universe is decided by the total density of matter. Note that  is not a constant over time.<br>
Where .<br>Now . Then the critical density today is<br>
<br><br>or equivalently<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/friedmann-equations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Friedmann Equations.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 08:43:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hubble Parameter]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Friedmann Equations" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/friedmann-equations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Friedmann Equations</a><br>
Definition<br>
and as a function of redshift<br>
<br>
<br>Peculiar velocity . See e.g. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ned.ipac.caltech.edu/level5/Watson/Watson2_2_1.html" target="_blank">https://ned.ipac.caltech.edu/level5/Watson/Watson2_2_1.html</a>
<br><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.astro.ljmu.ac.uk/~ikb/research/h-units.html" target="_blank">https://www.astro.ljmu.ac.uk/~ikb/research/h-units.html</a><br>While a lot of cosmology quantities are dependent (not physically, could be just  is used in the deduction) on hubble parameter, the precise value of Hubble constant are not decided yet. Therefore 2 common approach is, one, taking a fiducial value ( for example), or, embedding dimensionless parameter  into the unit.<br> is defined as<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/cosmology/hubble-parameter.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Cosmology/Hubble Parameter.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 23:14:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Coulomb's Law]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In SI units<br><br>Most advanced work is done in the Gaussian system, in which charge is measured in electrostatic units (esu)<br><br>Elementary particle physicists prefer the Heaviside-Lorentz system<br><br>The 3 units of charge are related as follows:<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/electrodynamics/coulomb's-law.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Electrodynamics/Coulomb's law.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:16:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Maxwell's equations]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Coulomb's law" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/electrodynamics/coulomb's-law.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Coulomb's law</a><br><br>(from Introduction to Classical Field Theory by Charles G. Torre)<br>
The force on a test particle with electric charge  at spacetime event  is given by<br><br>And the electromagnetic field is determined from the charge distribution that is present via the Maxwell equations<br><br>In geometric units<br><br>And in index notation with <br><br>Define electromagnetic tensor<br><br>Then the Maxwell equations becomes<br><br><br>Define scalar potential and vector potential, a scalar field  and a vector field  by<br>
By this definition  automatically satisfy second and fourth of the Maxwell equations. Define 4-potential . Then electromagnetic tensor is<br>
<br>The Lagrangian is given by<br>
and the action<br><br>The Euler-Lagrange equations<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/electrodynamics/maxwell's-equations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Electrodynamics/Maxwell's equations.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:16:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Energy Momentum relation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Or<br><br><br>We denote the spatial 3-momentum as  and 4-momentum , just to avoid confusion. Different literature may have different definition. <br><br>In geometrical units, ,<br><br>Or<br><br><br>It is also called the on-shell condition in QFT<br><br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/energy-momentum-relation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">General Relativity/Energy Momentum relation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 21:50:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Four Vectors]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Four-velocity is a tangent to the trajectory (4-velocity is ill-defined for photons, because )<br><br>By definition<br><br><br>for object with mass<br><br>By definition (in (-+++) convention)<br>
<br>For a photon<br><br>(recall definition of  and , )]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/four-vectors.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">General Relativity/Four Vectors.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 21:53:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lorentz Transformation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Four Vectors" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/four-vectors.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Four Vectors</a><br><br>Lorentz transformation is transformations that keep spacetime interval invariant, which is equivalent to, in matrix notation<br><br>or in index notation<br><br>A rotation free Lorentz transformation is called a Lorentz boost.<br>In the most well-known form,<br><br>where . For vector <br><br>It's important to keep in mind that vector  itself is invariant under Lorentz transformation/boost. It's merely the basis that is changing. Or explicitly<br><br>Where  is the inverse of .<br>The Lorentz boost from coordinate system  to  where  is moving at velocity  along the -axis of  is<br><br><br>(From Srednicki, 2)<br>
The set of all Lorentz transformations forms a group:<br>
<br>Associative: product of any two Lorentz transformations is also a Lorentz transformation.
<br>Identity: There exists an identity transformation that is a Lorentz transformation, 
<br>Every Lorentz transformation has an inverse
<br>Lorentz group has two important subgroups: <br>
<br>proper: ; improper: .
<br>orthochronous: . ( can only be  or ).
<br>We can write infinitesimal Lorentz Transformation as<br><br>the 6 degree of freedom can be completely decomposed to three rotations with infinitesimal angle () and three boosts with infinitesimal rapidity (),<br><br>Only proper and orthochronous transformations can be reached by compounding infinitesimal transformations. When a theory is said to be Lorentz invariant, this means under the proper orthochronous subgroup only.<br>Parity transformation, orthochronous but improper<br><br>and time-reversal transformation, nonorthochronous and improper<br><br>are usually discussed separately.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/lorentz-transformation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">General Relativity/Lorentz Transformation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 15:23:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Theory of General Relativity]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Jean carroll
<a data-href="Newtonian gravity#Newton's Theory of Gravitation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/astrophysics/newtonian-gravity.html#Newton's_Theory_of_Gravitation" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Newtonian gravity &gt; Newton's Theory of Gravitation</a> is an example of a dynamical system set within the context of Newtonian mechanics, while Maxwell's electromagnetism is a dynamical system operating within the context of special relativity.
<br>Spacetime interval  is defined as<br>
Geodesics equation<br>
Proper time  is defined as<br>
The proper time between two events measures the time elapsed as seen by an observer moving on a straight path between the events. Think of the twin paradox. In space, the shortest distance between two points is a straight line; in spacetime, the longest proper time between two events is a straight trajectory. For trajectory other than straight lines<br>
<br><br>Einstein's theory of gravity. Spacetime curves according to the Einstein's equation<br>
Objects move according to the geodesic equation<br>
<br><br><br><a data-href="Lorentz Transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/lorentz-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Lorentz Transformation</a>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/theory-of-general-relativity.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">General Relativity/Theory of General Relativity.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 11:30:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Vectors and Tensors]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Kronecker delta <br><br>Levi-Civita symbol <br><br><br><br>The only thing you cannot move is the order of , because  is not necessarily symmetric.<br>Product of matrices: <br>In calculation, from Einstein summation to matrix multiplication, if you want: R(C-R)C. Index close to each other are summed over.<br>The inverse of  is . The definition is . <br><br>Symmetric tensor <br>
Asymmetric tensor <br>the symmetric part of a (2,0) tensor <br>
the asymmetric part of a (2,0) tensor <br>
Always there is <br>For tensor more than two dimensions, sum over all permutations<br>
Symmetric <br>
Antisymmetric <br><br>Notation<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/vectors-and-tensors.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">General Relativity/Vectors and Tensors.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 22 Oct 2023 20:52:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bayesian Theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Application<br>
<a data-href="Markov Chain Monte Carlo" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/markov-chain-monte-carlo.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Markov Chain Monte Carlo</a><br>Bayes' theorem is used in Bayesian methods to update probabilities, which are degrees of belief, after obtaining new data. Given two events  and , the conditional probability of  given that  is true is expressed as follows<br><br>or<br><br>In a nutshell<br>
Symbol "" means "given". <br><br>Assume a signal  buried in some data . Probability that the signal has parameters  is<br>
<br>Thoughts<br>
<br>Likelihood: The probability of observing the data assuming that a particular set of parameters is true.
<br>Prior: Represents our state of knowledge about the true parameters before measuring the data.
<br>Posterior: Represents our state of knowledge about the parameters after measuring the data.<br>

]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/bayesian-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Bayesian Theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 07 Dec 2023 15:41:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Calculus for Physicists]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Before talking at all about other concepts, it is important to add some remarks about the widely used Leibnitz notation. See <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1784671/when-can-we-not-treat-differentials-as-fractions-and-when-is-it-perfectly-ok" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1784671/when-can-we-not-treat-differentials-as-fractions-and-when-is-it-perfectly-ok" target="_blank">When can we not treat differentials as fractions? And when is it perfectly OK?</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/73492/how-misleading-is-it-to-regard-fracdydx-as-a-fraction" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/73492/how-misleading-is-it-to-regard-fracdydx-as-a-fraction" target="_blank">How misleading is it to regard&nbsp;𝑑𝑦/𝑑𝑥&nbsp;as a fraction?</a>. The last question have more examples when this goes wrong. The practical summary is that  looks like and works like a fraction in multiplication and division within first order, as a result of the chain rule. And  almost never works like a fraction.<br>for example, these operations are correct<br><br>while these are not<br><br>The first one can be made correct with a negative sign<br><br>and the second one is plain nonsense.<br>It is also fun / useful to check out <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1024280/most-ambiguous-and-inconsistent-phrases-and-notations-in-maths" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/1024280/most-ambiguous-and-inconsistent-phrases-and-notations-in-maths" target="_blank">Most ambiguous and inconsistent phrases and notations in maths</a><br><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_function" target="_blank">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Continuous_function</a><br>
<br>Epsilon-delta (Weierstrass and Jordan) definition -- a special case for real functions
<br>Definition in terms of neighbourhoods -- the general definition

Other facts
<br> continuous: -th derivative exists and is continuous.
<br>Smooth is  continuous: infinitely differentiable.
<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/3614200/partial-derivatives-with-only-one-variable-held-constant" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/3614200/partial-derivatives-with-only-one-variable-held-constant" target="_blank">Partial derivatives with only one variable held constant</a><br>
The rule of thumb is to make clear in partial derivative what is kept constant. For example, the partial derivative  for  usually means to keep  constant, regardless of further information how might  depend on  or . If further down the line we know that  is dependent on  by . Then  would be a different function! In this case it is better to state explicitly (when it is unclear from context) if only  is or both  are kept constant when you write . It is also tempting to ask how can  variate without changing ? This is because we simply forget that fact that  when writing . <br>Furthermore,  here by it self means nothing more than , it is a map that takes a vector of three components and output a number. There is no 'dependence' whatsoever about components of the vector! Adding the information  later simply creates a new function, say , that has nothing to do with . However the notation is often abused to keep calling this new function , then you should be careful about what is kept constant to see whether the partial derivative of question is  or . <br><br><br>Some useful Taylor expansions and their radii of convergence<br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><a data-href="Gaussian integral" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/gaussian-integral.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gaussian integral</a>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/calculus.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Calculus.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 23:08:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Campbell-Baker-Hausdorf formula]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>For non-commutative ,<br><br>Its dual is called the the Zassenhaus formula, which is equally (some might say more) useful in Quantum Field Theory,<br><br>or in a simpler form<br><br>where  are polynomials in  of degree .<br>What this formula do is basically allowing us to break up exponentials for small non-commutating operators .]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/campbell-baker-hausdorf-formula.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Campbell-Baker-Hausdorf formula.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 16:24:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Central limit theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>If  for  independent variables , then for , we have  Gaussian.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/central-limit-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Central limit theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 12:41:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Coordinate Transformation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Cartisian coordinates  becomes  after linear transformation . For any vector in space  we have<br><br>This is to say, linear transformation  can be regarded either as a transformation of the vector coordinates or a transformation of the coordinates, depends on what you want to do.<br>This way the components of the same vector  in new coordinates is given by<br><br>The transposed form of above equations are used more often for the form of components transformation is easier<br><br>It follows that <br><br>If  is orthogonal transformation (orthogonal matrix) then<br><br>which is the formula in 《天文学教程》and《球面天文学》.<br><br>A matrix  is called orthogonal if<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/coordinate-transformation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Coordinate Transformation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 23:01:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Differential Equations for Physicists]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A wave equation looks like<br><br>or you can use Laplacian  in place of .]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/differential-equations-for-physicists.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Differential Equations for Physicists.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 19 Oct 2023 23:10:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Differential Geometry for Physicists]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The main purpose of this page is for the discussion of <a data-href="Theory of General Relativity" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/general-relativity/theory-of-general-relativity.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Theory of General Relativity</a>.<br>
Reference: Carroll (Spacetime and Geometry)<br><br>An open ball  in :   An open set : the arbitrary union of open balls / any point  can be the center of a open ball completely inside.<br>
A chart / coordinate system: subset  plus a one-to-one map , such that  is an open set (henceforth we can say  is an open set in ).  A  atlas of set : a collection of charts where the union of open sets is equal to  and the maps are sewed smoothly together - where the translation (transformation) between every two charts are infinitely differentiable, i.e. , then . <br>Finally we define manifold<br><br>Some remarks<br>
<br> can be substitute with  for definition of  n-manifold. But we study smooth () ones here.
<br> of a chart is required to be open. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/2127756/why-do-coordinate-charts-require-open-sets" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/2127756/why-do-coordinate-charts-require-open-sets" target="_blank">Why do charts require open sets?</a> 
<br>The opening of  is defined following the opening of .
<br>Despite a.k.a coordinate systems, charts differs from our usual notion of coordinate system by the requirement that  is open. E.g. the spherical coordinate system  is closed, and therefore not a chart. 
<br>I find the name "coordinate transformation" quite misleading. Changing your language of describing the same thing is not transformation, it should be called translation.
<br>Examples of manifolds<br>
<br>n-dimensional Euclidean space 
<br>n-sphere 
<br>n-torus 
<br>two-torus with  holes, Riemann surfaces of genus 
<br>In GR, the smooth manifold is the spacetime itself.  coordinate system is a chart in the  manifold. For example, Schwarzschild metric is a (0,2) tensor defined in the manifold. The coordinate singularity at  is merely a bad patch of our map which could be removed in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kruskal%E2%80%93Szekeres_coordinates" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kruskal%E2%80%93Szekeres_coordinates" target="_blank">Kruskal-Szekeres coordinates</a>. The only singularity in this spacetime is the physical singularity at . We can easily remove and have a perfect smooth manifold left. <br>See this excellent question and answer <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/705091/coordinate-singularity-in-general-relativity-and-smooth-structure-of-a-manifold" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/705091/coordinate-singularity-in-general-relativity-and-smooth-structure-of-a-manifold" target="_blank">Coordinate singularity in general relativity and smooth structure of a manifold</a><br><br><br>e.g. SO(2) and  (1-sphere, circle) are diffeomorphic.<br><br>A curve is . A curve "parametrized by " simply means we denote the variable  as , and , a number  corresponds to a point  on the curve  in the manifold . Sometimes when we say "a curve ", it means , where a specific coordinate system is used.  is a representation of a curve under a chosen coordinate system. Keep in mind that a curve itself is independent of coordinate choice. <br>A function is  (unless stated otherwise). Similar to the case of curve,  means . A function on a manifold is like a scalar field.<br>A vector at a point  is defined as a directional derivative operator . When acting on a function<br><br>meaning any vector can be decomposed in basis of , i.e. , this choice of basis  is called a coordinate basis. There are also non-coordinate basis. A vector at  maps a function at  to a number, while a vector field maps a function () to a function ().<br>A one-form  can be expressed in term of the coordinate basis of one-forms: . The gradient of a function act on directional derivative operator as<br><br>(easier to understand in Euclidean space ) The set of basis matches properly because .<br>A  tensor<br><br><br>The (0,2) metric tensor , the basis is the <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensor_product" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tensor_product" target="_blank">tensor product</a> of two basis one-forms or basis dual vectors. But as  is taken to represent the determinant of the metric. We use<br><br>we call  "metric" and "line element" interchangeably. But keep in mind it is a tensor, written in components  basis. Also keep in mind  here is actually our honest (0,2) tensor , and . (Tensor product does not commute)<br><br>
<br>Any -manifold can be embedded in  (Whitney's embedding theorem)
<br>A Klein bottle is an example of a 2-manifold that cannot be embedded in 
<br>"In principle, tensor components need not change when we change coordinates, they change when we change the basis in the tangent space, but we have decided to use the coordinates to define our basis. Therefore a change of coordinates induces a change of basis"
<br>"The word Euclidean sometimes means that the space is flat, and sometimes doesn't, but it always means that the canonical form is strictly positive; the terminology is unfortunate but standard."
<br>On dx notation ⚠️
Most references are not sufficiently picky to distinguish between "," the informal notion of an infinitesimal displacement, and "" the rigorous notion of a basis one-form given by the gradient of a coordinate function. (They also tend to neglect the fact that tensor products don't commute, and write expressions like  as ; it should be clear what is meant from the context.) In fact our notation "" does not refer to the differential of anything, or the square of anything; it's just conventional shorthand for the metric tensor, a multilinear map from two vectors to the real numbers." - Carroll
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/differential-geometry.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Differential Geometry.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 16:53:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Finite Element Method (FEM)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>For Laplace's equation<br><br>Q1: What is a good way to approximate functions that requires only finitely much data/computation?<br>
Q2: How do we find an approximation of the solution of a PDE without knowing the solution itself?<br>Approximation<br>
<br>(Finite) Fourier series
<br>A global polynomial (Taylor series)
<br>Local (piecewise) polynomicals defined on a subdivision (the "mesh") of the domain 
<br>...
<br>Commonly found features of solutions of PDEs:<br>
<br>Smooth in large parts of the domain
<br>Vary greatly in small parts of the domain
<br>May have kinks
<br>Singularities in corners
<br>Fourier approximation  - localized kinks ruin the whole approximation<br>
Taylor approximation  - localized kinks ruin the whole approximation<br>
Weierstrass approximation theorem<br>
Every function  that is bounded on an interval  can be approximated arbitrarily well by polynomials.<br>
They work only if the function is smooth in <br>Solution: Piecewise approximation!<br>
<br>Split the domain on which you want to approximate  into small parts
<br>Approximate separately on each part<br>
Advantages:
<br>We can use low-order approximations on each part
<br>Resolving kinks and singularities can be done locally
<br>We can increase the "resolution" where necessary - "(h-)adaptive mesh refinement (AMR)" - e.g. 10 cheaper in 2D, 100 cheaper in 3D
<br>We can increase the polynomial degree where the solution is smooth - "p-adaptive mesh refinement"
<br><br>Assume you have a function  on an interval <br>It's "interpolant", say, :<br>
<br>Also a function on 
<br>Has polynomial degree 
<br>Is equal to  at  points :<br>

<br>HYJ: How to choose ?<br>Theorem (not optimal, but good enough):<br>
Assume that  is  times continuously differentiable. Then independent of the choise of the points <br>
 p-th derivative of <br>
Read this as<br>
Consequence:<br>
<br>If  does not grow too quickly, then  as <br>
Problem:  on 
<br>Polynomial approximant is not guaranteed to converge! (as  increase)
<br>A better approach: keep  constant and instead split the interval into  pieces<br>
Theorem:<br>
Consequence: Pick a , choose enough intervals , and you can make the difference as small as you want!<br>HYJ: "Assume that  is  times continuously differentiable" ... <br>Denote the diameter of intervals/cells by :<br>
<br>Two other estimates (also works in 2D and 3D):<br>
L2-norm<br><br>Gradient norm / energy norm / h1 semi-norm<br><br>averaging difference of gradient]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/finite-element-method-(fem).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Finite Element Method (FEM).md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 13:00:22 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gaussian distribution]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The 1-D gaussian probability distribution takes the form<br><br>the normalization prefactor  is found by . This integral can be solved by a coordinate transformation to  can calculating the square of this integral, see <a data-href="Gaussian integral" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/gaussian-integral.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Gaussian integral</a>. <br>Often denoted as  or . <br><img alt="3sigma.jpg" src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/attachments/3sigma.jpg"><br>Properties:<br>
<br>If , then , .
<br><br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/gaussian-distribution.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Gaussian distribution.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:24:00 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/attachments/3sigma.jpg" length="0" type="image/jpeg"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/attachments/3sigma.jpg"&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gaussian integral]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The Gaussian integral takes the form<br><br><br><br>Proof:<br>
To calculate the Gaussian integral, consider the square of a Gaussian and integrate in polar coordinate . Set<br><br>then consider the double integral <br><br>Hence<br><br><br>Gaussian integral with imaginary width is often used in Quantum physics, in the context of path integral. The Gaussian integral can be extended to imaginary width, as following,<br><br>The integral is proved by calculating the contour integral  along a trajectory involving a straight line on the real axis from <br>A calculation:<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/368186/gaussian-integral-with-imaginary-coefficients-and-wick-rotation" target="_blank">https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/368186/gaussian-integral-with-imaginary-coefficients-and-wick-rotation</a>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/gaussian-integral.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Gaussian integral.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2025 12:11:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Geometry]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>For a plane , the normal vector of the plane is . The plane equation can be rewritten as , i.e. , where  is some point on the plane.<br>The distance of some point  to a plane  is<br>
Proof:<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/geometry.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Geometry.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 04:33:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Group Theory for Physicists]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>A group is a non-empty set  together with a binary operation on , denoted "", s.t.  .  is a group if the following three requirements, known as group axioms are satisfied:<br>(Closure )<br>
Associativity ,<br>
Identity element ,<br>
Inverse element .]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/group-theory-for-physicists.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Group Theory for Physicists.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2023 02:41:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hilbert Space]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>A&nbsp;Hilbert space&nbsp;is a&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Real number" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real_number" target="_blank">real</a>&nbsp;or&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_number" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Complex number" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_number" target="_blank">complex</a>&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner_product_space" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Inner product space" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inner_product_space" target="_blank">inner product space</a>&nbsp;that is also a&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_metric_space" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Complete metric space" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_metric_space" target="_blank">complete metric space</a>&nbsp;with respect to the distance function&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induced_topology" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Induced topology" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Induced_topology" target="_blank">induced</a>&nbsp;by the inner product.<br>To say that a complex vector space&nbsp;&nbsp;is a&nbsp;complex inner product space&nbsp;means that there is an inner product&nbsp;&nbsp;associating a complex number to each pair of elements&nbsp;&nbsp;of&nbsp;&nbsp;that satisfies the following properties:<br>
<br>The inner product is conjugate symmetric; that is, the inner product of a pair of elements is equal to the&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_conjugate" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Complex conjugate" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_conjugate" target="_blank">complex conjugate</a>&nbsp;of the inner product of the swapped elements: More importantly, this implies that &nbsp;is a real number.
<br>The inner product is&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_functional" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Linear functional" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_functional" target="_blank">linear</a>&nbsp;in its first&nbsp;argument. For all complex numbers&nbsp;&nbsp;and&nbsp;<br>

<br>The inner product of an element with itself is&nbsp;<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Definite_bilinear_form" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" title="Definite bilinear form" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Definite_bilinear_form" target="_blank">positive definite</a>:&nbsp;
<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/hilbert-space.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Hilbert Space.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 23:05:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Inference]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>From lecture notes of modern astrostatistics, Elena Sellentin<br><br><br>where<br>
<br> is the human theories
<br> is the data provided by nature
<br>Likelihood 
<br>: prior probability of 
<br><br>Therefore the integral  does not necessarily . Hence the "normalization" of likelihood over parameter space not only doesn't matter, but is also meaningless. <br>See<br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/2641/what-is-the-difference-between-likelihood-and-probability" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/2641/what-is-the-difference-between-likelihood-and-probability" target="_blank">What is the difference between "likelihood" and "probability"?</a><br>
<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/31238/what-is-the-reason-that-a-likelihood-function-is-not-a-pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/31238/what-is-the-reason-that-a-likelihood-function-is-not-a-pdf" target="_blank">What is the reason that a likelihood function is not a pdf?</a><br>For discrete data points  and corresponding data  predicted by a model with parameters ,  is defined as<br>
where  is the uncertainty in the measurement of . (Not deviation from mean)<br>If the likelihood takes a Gaussian form (which is not always the case! but we use this all the time so beware!), the likelihood is related to  in<br>
Maximizing the likelihood is hence minimizing . In parameter inference we can choose to maximize   or  or to minimize  as we please. According to our problem and algorithm, some cases works better than others.<br>
The likelihood is&nbsp;not&nbsp;the probability of the parameter value being correct&nbsp;or anything like that -&nbsp;it is the probability (density)&nbsp;of the data given the parameter value, which is a completely different thing. Therefore one should not expect the likelihood function to behave like a probability density.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/inference.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Inference.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 10:25:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Lie Theory]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZRca3Ggpy_g" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZRca3Ggpy_g" target="_blank">YouTube series by Mathemaniac</a> are very good.<br>
<a data-href="Group Theory for Physicists" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/group-theory-for-physicists.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Group Theory for Physicists</a><br>
<a data-href="Rotations" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/rotations.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Rotations</a><br>A Lie group is a group (the 4 axioms) and also a manifold -&gt; Lie algebra<br>For any continuous group, the transformations that lie infinitesimally close to the identity define a vector space, called the Lie algebra of the group. The basis vectors for this vector space are called the generators of the Lie algebra, or of the group. <br>It is generally true that one can find matrix representations of a continuous group by finding matrix representations of the generators of the group (which must satisfy the proper commutation relations), then exponentiating these infinitesimal transformations. (3.1, Peskin &amp; Schroeder)<br>Rotation generators , which satisfy the commutation relations . Finite rotation operations are therefore . In two dimension matrix representation is .<br><br>Space with basis of matrx basis  , for example, Pauli matrices.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/lie-theory.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Lie Theory.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2023 10:28:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Markov Chain Monte Carlo]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Based on <a data-href="Bayesian Theorem" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/bayesian-theorem.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Bayesian Theorem</a><br>
In statistics, Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) methods comprise a class of algorithms for sampling from a probability distribution. By constructing a Markov chain that has the desired distribution as its equilibrium distribution, one can obtain a sample of the desired distribution by recording states from the chain. The more steps that are included, the more closely the distribution of the sample matches the actual desired distribution. Various algorithms exist for constructing chains, including the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm.<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://youtu.be/yApmR-c_hKU" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/yApmR-c_hKU</a><br>
A sampling method.<br>
<br>Markov Chain: next sample depends on last
<br>Monte Carlo: random sampling<br>
After some burn-in samples, the samples after is (we wish) the stationary distribution, which has the desired probability distribution .
<br>How to design the Markov Chain? Stationary distribution to be   detailed balance condition Summing  over both sides shows why this is the condition of stationary distribution<br><br>where  is the transition matrix. Notice  is just the matrix multiplication.<br><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://youtu.be/yCv2N7wGDCw" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/yCv2N7wGDCw</a><br>
Function: to sample from  when we have only , where , where  is some normalizing factor. This is often the case in Bayesian inference. <br><br>where  is often infeasible.<br>
<br>Propose a sample according to <br>
The next candidate is sampled from some distribution according to the previous candidate. e.g. The next candidate is sampled from a normal distribution centered on the previous candidate.

The Metropolis algorithm refers to symmetric distribution here, and the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm is more general.
<br>Accept to acceptance probability <br>
The detailed balance condition, for any state 

Therefore

if , then , <br>
if , then , 
<br>So<br><br>This way the acceptance probability is set in such way that the transition probability in the constructed Markov chain will satisfy the detailed balance condition, i.e. the equilibrium condition. This is how the equilibrium distribution of the Markov chain can resemble the posterior.<br>For intuition, let  be symmetric. Consider Metropolis algorithm<br><br>if , then <br>
if , then , the lower  is relative to , the less likely next sample will go there.<br><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://youtu.be/7LB1VHp4tLE" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/7LB1VHp4tLE</a><br>
Used when you want to sample 2 or more dimensional distribution. Use Gibbs sampling when sampling from  is difficult but sampling from ,  is easy.<br>Procedure<br>
<br>Start at 
<br>Sample 
<br>Sample , then  is the next sample. 
<br>go to 2 and repeat.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/markov-chain-monte-carlo.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Markov Chain Monte Carlo.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 04:39:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Matrices]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>The determinant is a&nbsp;multiplicative map
<br>Trace is invariant under circular shifts 
<br><br><br>In linear algebra, a square matrix  is called diagonalizable or non-defective if it is similar to a diagonal matrix, i.e., if there exists an invertible matrix  and a diagonal matrix  such that , or equivalently  (such ,  are not unique.)<br><br>In linear algebra, an orthogonal matrix is a real square matrix whose columns and rows are orthonormal vectors, or equivalently , or . <br>
<br>An orthogonal matrix is necessarily invertible, unitary (), and therefore normal () over the real numbers. The determinant of any orthogonal matrix is either  or . 
<br>Real symmetric matrices are diagonalizable by orthogonal matrices. More generally, matrices are diagonalizable by unitary matrix if and only if they are normal.
<br><br>In linear algebra, an invertible complex square matrix  is unitary if its conjugate transpose  is also its inverse, that is, if .<br>In quantum theory, <a data-href="Unitary transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unitary transformation</a> are linked with <a data-href="Conservation laws" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/conservation-laws.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Conservation laws</a> and are hence of great interest.<br><br>A complex square matrix  is normal if it commutes with its conjugate transpose , i.e. .<br>
<br>A matrix is normal if and only if it is unitarily similar to a diagonal matrix, and therefore any matrix  satisfying the equation  is diagonalizable. 
<br> is the transposed conjugate of . In quantum mechanics it is often called Hermitian adjoint and denoted as .<br><br>A matrix (or a order-two tensor) can always be decomposed into trace, an anti-symmetric part, and a traceless symmetric part.<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/matrices.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Matrices.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2025 15:30:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Multivariate Calculus]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>For <br><br>In another form, often used in thermodynamics<br><br><br>Del (nabla) operator in Cartisian coordinates<br>
Del (nabla) operator in cylindrical coordinates<br>
Del (nabla) operator in spherical coordinates<br>
<br>Laplacian<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/multivariate-calculus.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Multivariate Calculus.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 07:19:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Nearest Neighbor]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>1 Dimension<br>
brute force: <br>
binary tree: <br>d Dimension: real  dimensional space <br>
the distance between any two points can be computed in  time<br>
brute force: <br>
k-dimensional trees: between  and <br><br>The k-d tree is a binary tree in which every node is a k-dimensional point. Every non-leaf node can be thought of as implicitly generating a splitting hyperplane that divides the space into two parts, known as half-spaces. Points to the left of this hyperplane are represented by the left subtree of that node and points to the right of the hyperplane are represented by the right subtree. The hyperplane direction is chosen in the following way: every node in the tree is associated with one of the k dimensions, with the hyperplane perpendicular to that dimension's axis. So, for example, if for a particular split the "x" axis is chosen, all points in the subtree with a smaller "x" value than the node will appear in the left subtree and all points with a larger "x" value will be in the right subtree. In such a case, the hyperplane would be set by the x value of the point, and its normal would be the unit x-axis. (standard kd tree splitting rule)<br>default tree constrution algorithm: sliding midpoint rule<br>
default search algorithm: <br>The algorithm operates recursively.  When first encountering a node of the kd-tree the algorithm first visits the child that is closest to the query point. On return, if the box containing the other child lies within  times the distance to the closest point seen so far, then the other child is visited recursively.<br>Note from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~mount/Papers/dist.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.cs.umd.edu/~mount/Papers/dist.pdf" target="_blank">Arya et al. 1998</a><br>
 space and  query time are achievable in the expected case through the use of kd-trees (Friedman, Bentley and Finkel, 1977). The constant factors hidden in the asymptotic running time grow at least as fast as  (depending on the metric). From the perspective of worst-case performance, an ideal solution would be to preprocess the points in  time, into a data structure requiring  space so that queries can be answered in  time.<br>Main result from Arya et al. (1998) is stated in the following theorem<br>
Theorem 1. Consider a set  of  data points in . There is a constant , such that in  time it is possible to construct a data structure of size , such that for any Minkowski metric:<br>
<br>Given any  and , a -approximate nearest neighbor of  in  can be reported in  time
<br>More generally, given , , and any , , a sequence of  -approximate nearest neighbors of  in  can be computed in  time.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/nearest-neighbor.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Nearest Neighbor.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 01:25:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Plancherel theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>From <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parseval%27s_theorem" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parseval%27s_theorem" target="_blank">Parseval's theorem</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plancherel_theorem" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plancherel_theorem" target="_blank">Plancheral theorem</a><br>
That is, if  is a function on the real line, and  is its frequency spectrum, then<br><br>The unitarity of the Fourier transform is often called Parseval's theorem in science and engineering fields, based on an earlier (but less general) result that was used to prove the unitarity of the Fourier series.<br><br>Alternatively, for the discrete Fourier transform (DFT), the relation becomes:<br><br>When  is the DFT of <br><br>Proof<br><br>Q.E.D.<br>A python script to verify Plancheral theorem. See <a data-href="Velocity Power Spectra#Appendix B Fourier Transform in np fft and in physics" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/Velocity Power Spectra#Appendix B Fourier Transform in np fft and in physics" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Velocity Power Spectra &gt; Appendix B Fourier Transform in np fft and in physics</a> about the impletation of DFT in Numpy.<br>import numpy as np
N = 50
f = np.random.rand(N,N,N)
g = np.fft.fftn(f)
print(1/N**3 * np.sum(np.abs(g)**2))
print(np.sum(f**2))
<br>or<br>```python
import numpy as np
N = 50
f = np.random.rand(N,N,N)
g = np.fft.fftn(f, norm="ortho")
print(np.sum(np.abs(g)**2))
print(np.sum(f**2))
<br>You will find the two quantity printed here will be equal (with a little error).]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/plancherel-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Plancherel theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2023 20:16:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Rotations]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>Rotation is linear -&gt; hence matrix representation

<br>
<br>


<br>Preserves lengths and angles -&gt; preserve dot product<br>

<br>Preserves orientation  
<br>In summary<br><br>They are called the orthogonal or unitary matrices<br><br><br><br><br>
<br>Rotational matrices are orthogonal matices: 
<br>The different sign of  is not a mistake, think about it. It follows the permutation: zxy, xyz, yzx (instead of yxz). 
<br>Multiplying rotation matrix to the right is rotating the vector by 


]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/rotations.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Rotations.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 22:58:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Basic terminologies]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Expectation  or Mean . For discrete distribution , <br><br> For continuous distribution ,<br><br>In general the expectation value of  is,<br><br>Properties:<br>
<br>Linearity: 
<br>When in doubt, go back to integral.
<br>Variance  or . For discrete distribution , probability of  being <br><br>For continuous distribution , probability of  be in <br><br>In general,<br><br>Properties:<br>
<br>
<br>
<br>
<br>
<br><br>covariance is the tendency in linear relationship<br><br>or in another notation (and assuming real)<br><br>or<br><br>\Sigma := \begin{pmatrix}<br>
\mathrm{Var}(X) &amp; \mathrm{Cov}(X,Y) \<br>
\mathrm{Cov}(Y,X) &amp; \mathrm{Var}(Y)<br>
\end{pmatrix}<br><br>C = \langle \boldsymbol{n} \boldsymbol{n}^T\rangle<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/statistics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Statistics.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 12:31:50 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Vector Space]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The wikipedia page for <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vector_space" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vector_space" target="_blank">vector space</a> is good enough so I used the definition there<br>A vector space over a field  is a non-empty set  together with a binary operation and a binary function that satisfy the eight axioms listed below. <br>
<br>The binary operation, called vector addition or simply addition assigns to any two vectors  and  in  a third vector in  which is commonly written as , and called the sum of these two vectors.
<br>The binary function, called scalar multiplication, assigns to any scalar  in  and any vector  in  another vector in , which is denoted .
<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/vector-space.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Math/Vector Space.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 22:59:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Anti-unitary operator]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>where  is an <a data-href="Unitary transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unitary transformation</a> and  is complex conjugation, analogy to rotation + reflection.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/anti-unitary-operator.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Anti-unitary operator.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:30:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Berry phase]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Adiabatic evolution with return to starting point, final state can only differ from initial state by a phase factor (for a non-degenerate state)<br><br>There are two phase factors, one is a dynamical phase factor, depending on the period  of the cycle. The other is called Berry phase, or geometric phase, independent on ,<br><br>where  is the parameter given by .]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/berry-phase.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Berry phase.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 23:30:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Bohr-Sommerfeld quantization]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>A semiclassical quantization, discovered before the Schrödinger equation. For periodic motion, phase accumulated in one period should be an integer multiple of <br><br>
<br> the canonical momentum (not an operator!)
<br> is a phase shift picked up at two turning points,  at a hard wall (e.g. infinite potential well),  at a smooth turning point.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/bohr-sommerfeld-quantization.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Bohr-Sommerfeld quantization.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 21:34:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Conservation laws]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>If under a unitary transformation the Hamiltonian is invariant<br><br>it also follows that the observable corresponding to the Hermitian operator  is conserved<br><br>where . Recall that any <a data-href="Unitary transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unitary transformation</a>  can be written with a <a data-href="Hermitian operator" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/hermitian-operator.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hermitian operator</a> . ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/conservation-laws.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Conservation laws.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:30:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Cross section]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>
Cross-section in  reactions<br><br>where  is a matrix element - probability of scattering - for a particular choice of incoming and outgoing momenta  and .<br>
<br>Cross-section can depend only on Lorentz invariant quantities. e.g. masses of particles, coupling constants, centre of mass energy .
<br>If all incoming particles are relativistic, , we expect that total cross section is a function of center-of-mass energy only.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/cross-section.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Cross section.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:23:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dirac equation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Source: lecture Origin and Structure of the Standard Model<br><br><br><br>relativistic S equation -&gt; spin!<br>Plane wave solution<br>
Feynman slash notation <br>
Commute with Hamiltonian -&gt; conserved quantity / observable<br>helicity &amp; chirality.<br>
In massless case helicity and chirality either coincide or interchange.<br>
In massive case chirality is not an observable . (helicity always is, )<br>
We interpret helicity with chirality, helicity itself is algebraic.<br>4 degrees of freedom, +- energy, +- helicity/chirality<br>but what is - energy solution?<br>EM field<br>gauge invariance - (you can at most say A is pure gauge, but not zero)<br>
generalized momentum <br>
Dirac Hamiltonian -&gt; can do perturbation theory<br>if there is negative energy states, then vacuum is unstable<br>"Representation" - basis<br>
For - E solution -&gt; C -&gt; build + E solution<br>
What does it mean? -&gt; change the charge!<br>Dirac sea? -&gt; positron + electron pair! if enough energy<br>where mathematics were not rigorous<br>Quantization of EM field<br>
E, B -&gt; 6 - 2 ( Bianchi identity) - 1 () - 1 ()<br>
= 2 degrees of freedom ~ 2 polarization<br>
EOM -&gt; of time<br>continuous limit: large volume, small spacing<br>
-&gt; creation / annihilation operator<br>Quantum harmonic oscillator * N -&gt; QFT<br>Particles is an intrinsic feature of perturbation theory (eigenvectors of free Hamiltonian), which makes the perturbation theory fundamental. ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/dirac-equation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Dirac equation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 14:16:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Fermions and bosons]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>statistics of identical particles, sum over all permutations  with parity <br><br><br>Symmetric under exchange<br><br><br>Antisymmetric under exchange<br>Alternative description: Fock space, many-particle state in terms of occupation numbers<br><br>where the vacuum state is defined by .<br>number operator <br>bosons: <br>
fermions: ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/fermions-and-bosons.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Fermions and bosons.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 13:54:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Feynman propagator]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propagator" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propagator" target="_blank">Feynman propagator</a> is a Green's function for the Klein-Gordon equation<br><br>It is<br><br>The -prescription is <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/379446/i-epsilon-in-the-expression-of-feynman-propagator" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/379446/i-epsilon-in-the-expression-of-feynman-propagator" target="_blank">useful</a> for indicating which way to go around the contour (see also <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/603365/why-is-the-i-epsilon-prescription-necessary-in-the-klein-gordon-propagator" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/603365/why-is-the-i-epsilon-prescription-necessary-in-the-klein-gordon-propagator" target="_blank">this question</a>). <br>Fourier transform of a propagator is defined as<br><br>where we can read off the Fourier space Feynman propagator<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/feynman-propagator.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Feynman propagator.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:37:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Field operators]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>commutator .<br>particle density operator <br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/field-operators.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Field operators.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:06:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gauge transformation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>gauge transformation = <a data-href="Unitary transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unitary transformation</a><br>
, all observables unaffected... except if  is no longer single-valued<br>In quantum mechanics the Schrödinger equation for EM field is<br><br>Gauge transformation  is equivalent to  with . This can be verified by checking ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/gauge-transformation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Gauge transformation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 20:48:28 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Heisenberg picture]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The Heisenberg equation of motion is<br><br>which assumes time dependence in operators rather than states, as opposed to the <a data-href="Schrödinger picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/schrödinger-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Schrödinger picture</a>. The Heisenberg picture is very useful along with <a data-href="Path integral" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/path-integral.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Path integral</a> in quantum field theory.<br>Some implications:<br>
<br>
The time evolution of a operator is therefore, 

We take . You can see this by substituting into the above Heisenberg equation of motion. If generalised to four vectors

where .

<br>
The Heisenberg equation implies that operator commuting with the Hamiltonian implies conservation, as in the quantity is invariant in evolution. If , then<br>


<br>
We can define instantaneous eigenstates as

such that

Note the sign difference between here  and the <a data-href="Schrödinger picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/schrödinger-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Schrödinger picture</a> where .

]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/heisenberg-picture.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Heisenberg picture.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 18:45:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hellmann-Feynman theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>For ,<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/hellmann-feynman-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Hellmann-Feynman theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 23:39:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Hermitian operator]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>An operator  is Hermitian (a.k.a. self-adjoint) if<br><br>Hermitian operator  is called an observable. Self-adjoint operators have real eigenvalues. <br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/633170/are-observables-in-qft-actually-observable" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/633170/are-observables-in-qft-actually-observable" target="_blank">Are observables in QFT actually observable?</a>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/hermitian-operator.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Hermitian operator.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 12:46:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[LSZ Reduction formula]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Source: Srednicki<br><br>The basic formula for a scattering amplitude in terms of the fields of an interacting quantum field theory is the LSZ formula<br><br>for  incoming particles of momentum  and  outgoing particles of momentum . Provided that the field is normalized as<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/lsz-reduction-formula.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/LSZ Reduction formula.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 14:30:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Outline of quantum field theory]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>For a free-field theory (the free-field theory is in analogy to the harmonic oscillator), ,<br><br>by (4D, ) Fourier transform, integration by parts, change of path integral variable, we obtain<br><br>where  is called the <a data-href="Feynman propagator" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/feynman-propagator.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Feynman propagator</a><br><br>The correlation function can be calculated using the amazing property of the <a data-href="Path integral" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/path-integral.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Path integral</a>, by pulling out appropriate numbers of numbers of  and setting  afterwards<br><br>this is called Wick's theorem.<br>For a general lagrangian with <br><br>where the counter term is<br><br>We would like to evaluate<br><br>The  sign is because the  trick (which introduced the Feynman propagator) does not give us the correct normalisation and we would need to enforce  by hand. <br>Turns out we can omit the vacuum diagrams (ones with no sources/external legs) by employing , therefore  with , sum of diagrams excluding vacuum diagrams and with an overall factor of  to keep  real. <br>After fixing  we also want  such that the <a data-href="LSZ Reduction formula" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/lsz-reduction-formula.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">LSZ Reduction formula</a> is applicable later on. This is achieved by changing . We can always modify  such that  to some order of . The result is that we can also omit the tadpole diagrams, the ones that when a single line is cut, falls into two parts, one of which has no sources. This can be seen from<br>
Recalling  being the sum of the non-vacuum diagrams, if the diagram has two or more sources, then taking the derivatives will leave one with at least one , where evaluating at  would make them vanish. The only possible non-zero part is the ones with one source. However, we forced the sum of them to be zero by modifying . <br>In the end, we need to account for  in the counterterm, which introduces a new vertex, . This new vertex should be put onto the propagators and acts on one or the other propagators. This is a correction factor.<br>In the end<br><br>where  is the sum of all connected diagrams with no tadpoles and at least two sources, and including the counterterm vertices.<br>The field is normalised as<br><br>The state is normalised as<br><br>where  stands for the four vector  and  being the spatial part.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/outline-of-quantum-field-theory.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Outline of quantum field theory.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 23:47:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Path integral]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>We follow closely to Srednicki, Quantum Field Theory, Ch. 6.<br>An equivalent formulation of quantum mechanics is the path integral formulation (the others are the <a data-href="Schrödinger picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/schrödinger-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Schrödinger picture</a> and <a data-href="Heisenberg picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/heisenberg-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Heisenberg picture</a>). The path integral formulation is considerably more convoluted, however it provides valuable insights to extensions to quantum field theories. <br>In the path integral formulation, the amplitude goes to<br><br>Specifically, the probability that a particle at  position at time  to move to  at  is<br><br>Starting from , one can apply the <a data-href="Heisenberg picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/heisenberg-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Heisenberg picture</a> evolution, discretising  and inserting  position states ,  momentum states . Then applying the <a data-href="Campbell-Baker-Hausdorf formula" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/math/campbell-baker-hausdorf-formula.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Campbell-Baker-Hausdorf formula</a> (what this formula do is basically allowing us to break up exponentials for small non-commutating operators ) and neglecting  terms we can <br>Note:<br>
<br>What are  and ?

where  are each subsequent in time, , with . Same for . Note that we have  of  and  of .
<br>The path integral is a limit.
<br>If  is no more than quadratic in the momenta (as is the case for ), then we can integrate over , then

discretising over time steps of  and integrating over  gives a integration constant, which we absorb into the definition of 


<br>Property of the path integral: inserting an operator  is the same as multiplying in the integrand its eigenvalue . We take  from now on.

This can be seen by writing out the time evolutions in <a data-href="Heisenberg picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/heisenberg-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Heisenberg picture</a>, which is

discretising to  of  and inserting  complete position eigenstates , we have in between one , which we have  . And the rest is the same as the process earlier (at the beginning of this page). From this procedure we notice that it is only possible to pull out operators in a time ordered manner

where  is the time ordering operator: "the product(s) of operators to its right is to be ordered, not as written, but with operators at later times to the left of those at earlier times" (Srednicki, p. 45). This seems like a hindrance, what if we want other orders? It turns out time ordered products is all we need. See <a data-href="LSZ Reduction formula" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/lsz-reduction-formula.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">LSZ Reduction formula</a>.
<br>Now that given a hamiltonian/lagrangian, we should, in principle, be able to calculate the transition rate/probability between some initial  and final  state. <br><br>We can generalise to the field space path integral (also called functional integral). But in this case we don't directly talk about the transition rate from some  to , instead we are interested in the statistical properties, the n-point correlation functions, which is eventually linked to  via the <a data-href="LSZ Reduction formula" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/lsz-reduction-formula.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">LSZ Reduction formula</a>. To fight the fields, we bring out the cavalry (and jargons) of statistical mechanics. First we have the partition functions,<br><br><br>To be continued...]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/path-integral.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Path integral.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 19:43:45 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Pieces in standard model]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Antimatter counts as negative baryon/lepton number<br>
<br>Baryon number is always conserved.
<br>(Electric) charge is always conserved.
<br>Lepton number is always conserved. (separately for )
<br>Mass on the left hand side of the equation must be bigger than the mass on the right hand side. (Conservation of energy)
<br>Strangeness may be conserved, but not always. (In weak interactions it can change by 1)
<br>The angular momentum is conserved
<br><br>
<br>For massive particles , massless ones . 
<br>Which is why photons have 2 polarizations instead of 3. So do gluons.
<br>Neutrinos only have one polarization for each type (6 in total). 
<br>Particles with charges have antiparticles.
<br>Neutrons have antineutrions.
<br>Neutrions have antineutrons.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/pieces-in-standard-model.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Pieces in standard model.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 22:53:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Position and momentum representation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Position operator:<br>
Momentum operator:<br><br>Commutator<br><br>Useful identity:<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/position-and-momentum-representation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Position and momentum representation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 16:53:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Quantum adiabatic theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Quantization of adiabatic invariant (Ehrenfest)<br><br>no transition between energy levels if the Hamiltonian changes sufficiently slowly, which is that , and that the rate of change of this gap is small . <br>The transition breaking this condition is called the Landau-Zener transition,<br><br>we see that  if <br>
<br>The term adiabatic is often used to mean slow changing, semi-steady state.
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/quantum-adiabatic-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Quantum adiabatic theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 22:50:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Schrödinger picture]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Heisenberg picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/heisenberg-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Heisenberg picture</a><br>
<a data-href="Path integral" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/path-integral.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Path integral</a><br><br>The time-dependent Schrödinger equation describing a system's evolution of time<br><br>Where  is the state vector of the quantum system at time  and  is an observable, the Hamiltonian operator.<br>Solution of Schrödinger equation is a unitary transformation<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/schrödinger-picture.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Schrödinger picture.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 18:45:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Unitary transformation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Operator  is an unitary operator if<br>
or equivalently . Every unitary operator on a Hilbert space can be written as  where  is a <a data-href="Hermitian operator" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/hermitian-operator.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Hermitian operator</a>.<br>For a transformation, the state vectors change as , operators <br><br>the norm is preserved upon unitary transformation<br><br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitary_operator#Examples" target="_blank">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unitary_operator#Examples</a><br>
<br>Identity function
<br>Rotation
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Unitary transformation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 00:10:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Variational principle]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The lowest state  of  is bounded from below<br><br>or if  not normalized,<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/variational-principle.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Variational principle.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 21:27:48 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wave function and state vectors]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Schrödinger picture" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/schrödinger-picture.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Schrödinger picture</a><br><br>Wave functions and Dirac braket are entirely a difference in notation, more so than the Schrödinger and Heisenberg pictures. The correspondence between the wave function and braket is as follows,<br><br>By introducing a Hilbert space and regard wave functions as components of vectors, the possibilities other than position  and momentum  representations are opened. <br>Sometimes we write , this refers to the vector state represented by the wave function<br><br>Don't be confused by . When we write it inside a ket,  is no longer a wave function, in the same manner that  is the position eigen state and  is the position operator -- distinct object with same element in notation.<br><br>invariant under basis change <br>
<br>Trace
<br>Eigenvalues
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/wave-function-and-state-vectors.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Wave function and state vectors.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 16:26:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Wigner's theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Every symmetry  is either a <a data-href="Unitary transformation" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/unitary-transformation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Unitary transformation</a> or an <a data-href="Anti-unitary operator" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/anti-unitary-operator.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Anti-unitary operator</a>.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/wigner's-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/Wigner's theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:30:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[WKB approximation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Wenzel-Kramers-Brillouin + Jeffreys. Also a semiclassical approximation! Resembles <a data-href="Bohr-Sommerfeld quantization" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/bohr-sommerfeld-quantization.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Bohr-Sommerfeld quantization</a>.<br>
probability amplitude  that a particle from  reaches  is the sum of the amplitudes along all classical paths connecting  to <br><br>
<br>factor  is to keep current density  constant along path
<br>phase shift  (Maslov index) is  at hard wall, where , so that incident and reflected waves cancel. At a smooth turning point,  changes sign, .
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/quantum-mechanics/wkb-approximation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Quantum Mechanics/WKB approximation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 21:47:42 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Boltzmann & Saha Equation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Under Thermodynamic Equilibrium, for two energy state of an atom, Bolzmann equation gives the ratio of their number density according to temperature and their energy difference.<br><br><br>By extending Boltzmann equation into continuous states, Saha equation give the ratio of number density of atoms on two adjacent ionization levels.<br><br>Where  is the partition function<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/boltzmann-&amp;-saha-equation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Thermodynamics/Boltzmann &amp; Saha Equation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Jul 2023 11:33:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Equipartition Theorem]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The equipartition theorem shows that in thermal equilibrium, any degree of freedom (such as a component of the position or velocity of a particle) which appears only quadratically in the energy has an average energy of  and therefore contributes  to the system's heat capacity. This has many applications.<br>It follows that in thermal equilibrium, monatomic gas has an average energy  per particle. Monatomic gas has degree of freedom . An diatomic gas with  for they have .  here is average energy per particle.<br>A note on the Boltzmann constant  and ideal gas constant .  is a microscopic quantity, corresponds to number of particle while  is macroscopic, counting particles in mole.<br><br>For a blob of ideal gas, the total internal energy (kinetic energy without bulk movement energy, and no rest mass energy, so not the total energy of the gas) is<br><br>Note that this equation is valid only under nonrelativistic ideal monatomic gas in its rest frame, and does not generalize. <br>Discussion<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/262382/relativity-of-temperature-paradox" target="_blank">https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/262382/relativity-of-temperature-paradox</a><br>
<br>Note: relation with the adiabatic index . For monatomic gas  restores the factor of <br>
Internal energy per particle is


<br>Internal energy per unit mass 


<br><br>Integrating the Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution<br><br>where  is the kinetic energy. ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/equipartition-theorem.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Thermodynamics/Equipartition Theorem.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 10:09:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Laws of Thermodynamics]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br><br>Differential Form, for system in quasi-static process<br><br>Specific heat<br><br>The term  often vanishes in discussion of gas/fluid dynamics, this is because<br>
<br>All relevant nuclear reactions are frozen (), so .
<br>All relevant chemical reactions are frozon  or occurs so fast () that it and its inverse are in local thermal dynamic equilibrium ( for species involved in the interactions).<br>
If any relevant nuclear/chemical interaction have  then we would need to carefully keep track of the chemical or nuclear species and their chemical potentials.<br>
(Blandford and Thorne, Modern classical physics, box 13.2)
<br>It is often useful to write the equation in terms of per unit mass (multiplying with density  if you want per unit volume), consider for a mass <br><br>Enthalpy. Sometimes referred to as the injection energy, the amount of energy needed to put in the gas and also push away the surrounding gas.<br>
Per unit mass enthalpy is<br><br><br>Entropy<br>
When a closed thermodynamic system goes from equilibrium state 1 to equilibrium state 2, the entropies of these two states obeys the relation<br>
A irreversible process]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Thermodynamics/Laws of Thermodynamics.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:00:04 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Statistical Distributions: Maxwell-Boltzmann, Fermi-Dirac, and Bose-Einstein]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Expectation value (average) of parameter  following distribution  is given by,<br><br>where  is the momentum. <br>The Boltzmann constant  is set to 1. Also .<br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br><br>Where we restored the units from . ]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/statistical-distributions.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Thermodynamics/Statistical Distributions.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2025 11:34:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Thermodynamic Process]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="Laws of Thermodynamics" href="https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Laws of Thermodynamics</a><br><br><br><br>In thermodynamics, an isothermal process is a type of thermodynamic process in which the temperature T of a system remains constant: ΔT = 0. This typically occurs when a system is in contact with an outside thermal reservoir, and a change in the system occurs slowly enough to allow the system to be continuously adjusted to the temperature of the reservoir through heat exchange (see quasi-equilibrium). In contrast, an adiabatic process is where a system exchanges no heat with its surroundings (Q = 0).<br>In an isothermal process,<br><br><br>In thermodynamics, an adiabatic process is a type of thermodynamic process that occurs without transferring heat or mass between the thermodynamic system and its environment, no heating or cooling from dissipative processes, such as viscosity, thermal conductivity, or the emission and absorption of radiation. Some processes occur too rapidly for energy to enter or leave the system as heat (or heat transfer occurs too slowly), allowing a convenient adiabatic approximation. Adiabaticity is often an accurate idealization in fluid dynamics. In an adiabatic flow, there is only one thermodynamic degree of freedom (which is the main perk of adiabatic approximation).<br><br>In an adiabatic process,<br>
This is called the adiabatic relation<br>
or<br>
or<br><br>This final form is sometimes called the polytropic equation of state, with polytropic index , defined as . With the ideal gas law, adiabatic relation can also be written as<br><br>Where  is called adiabatic index. It is defined as<br><br>For monatomic gas , for radiation .<br><br><br>Differentiating the adiabtic relation ,<br>
For ideal gas<br>
Therefore<br>
Finally, sound speed is<br>
]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/thermodynamics/thermodynamic-process.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Thermodynamics/Thermodynamic Process.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 09:17:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>"What I cannot create, I do not understand."  -- Richard Feynman<br>The purpose of this website, these notes, are not to serve as an encyclopedia. But as a personal reminder to keep track of the understanding that I have on these materials. I often find myself doing the work that I once did, learning the things that I once learned, and get stuck on the problems that I once solved. This website will help keep track of those concepts, tricks, and insights, bit by bit.<br>The importance of note taking cannot be understated<br>
<a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/write-down-what-youve-done/" target="_blank">https://terrytao.wordpress.com/career-advice/write-down-what-youve-done/</a><br>This website is created using Obsidian and Flowershow.]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">index.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 09:40:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Stationary-action principle]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>For action , the path taken by the system between times&nbsp;&nbsp;and&nbsp;&nbsp;and configurations &nbsp;and &nbsp;is the one for which the&nbsp;action&nbsp;is&nbsp;stationary (no change)&nbsp;to&nbsp;first order. For many systems, the Lagrangian is .<br>The mathematical expression is<br><br>Euler-Lagrangian equation gives the equation of motion<br><br>Similarly the Euler-Lagrangian equation for fields  (a bunch of fields, hence the subscript ) is<br>]]></description><link>https://yujieh3.github.io/notes/stationary-action-principle.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Stationary-action principle.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Yujie He]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2025 14:20:04 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>